<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<resources>
    <string name="page01_title">A competition to identify bird calls using machine learning </string>
    <string name="page01_meta">
        Tom Denton\n
        Software Engineer, Chrome Media Audio\n
        Published Jun 16, 2020\n
    </string>
    <string name="page01_main">
        Do you hear the birds chirping outside your window? There are more than 10,000 bird species
        in the world, and they can be found in nearly every environment, from untouched rainforests
        to suburbs and cities. Birds play an essential role in nature. They are high up in the food
        chain and integrate changes occurring at low levels. As such, birds are excellent indicators
        of deteriorating habitat quality and environmental pollution. However, it’s often easier to
        hear birds than see them. With proper sound detection and classification, researchers could
        automatically intuit factors about an area’s quality of life based on a changing bird
        population.\n\n

        There are already many projects underway to extensively monitor birds by recording natural
        soundscapes over long periods. However the analysis of these datasets is often done
        manually, is painstakingly slow, and results are incomplete. Data science may be able
        to assist, so researchers have turned to large crowdsourced databases of vocal recordings
        of birds to train AI models.\n\n

        To fully take advantage of these extensive and information-rich sound archives, researchers need
        good machine listeners to reliably extract as much information as possible to aid
        data-driven conservation.\n\n

        In partnership with the Cornell Lab of Ornithology, Google’s bioacoustics team—part of our AI
        for Social Good initiative—is announcing a competition to use machine learning to identify
        bird calls. In this competition, data scientists will identify a wide variety of bird
        vocalizations in soundscape recordings. Training audio comes from the Xeno-Canto project,
        a crowd-sourced collection of thousands of hours of bird sounds from around the world.
        We’re offering $25,000 in prizes for the best entries, and hosting the competition on
        Kaggle, the world’s largest data science competition community with more than 4 million
        members from 194 countries. The competition kicks off today and will last until September
        2—check out the competition page for more details.\n\n

        If successful, winners of this competition will help researchers better understand changes in
        habitat quality, levels of pollution, and the effectiveness of restoration efforts.
        The eventual conservation outcomes could greatly improve the quality of life for many
        living organisms—birds and human beings included.\n\n
    </string>



</resources>